<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A most strange and vvonderfull prophesie vpon this troublesome world calculated by the famous doctor in astrologie, Maister Iohn Cypriano, conferred with the iudgements of Iames Marchecelsus and Sinnior Guinardo, three excellent astronomers v[n]der the emperour of Christendom ; sent out of Germany into Italy, to the Vniuersitie of Padua ... ; whereunto is annexed Tarquatus Vandermers seauen yeres study in the arte of magick, vpon the twelue moneths of the yeare ... ; translated out of Italian by Anth. Hollaway ...</title>
            <author>Cipriano, Giovanni.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1595</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 11 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 7 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A18901</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 5324.5_PARTIAL</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 24592_PARTIAL</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S294</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">22226613</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 22226613</idno>
            <idno type="VID">25249</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A18901)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 25249)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1749:1)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A most strange and vvonderfull prophesie vpon this troublesome world calculated by the famous doctor in astrologie, Maister Iohn Cypriano, conferred with the iudgements of Iames Marchecelsus and Sinnior Guinardo, three excellent astronomers v[n]der the emperour of Christendom ; sent out of Germany into Italy, to the Vniuersitie of Padua ... ; whereunto is annexed Tarquatus Vandermers seauen yeres study in the arte of magick, vpon the twelue moneths of the yeare ... ; translated out of Italian by Anth. Hollaway ...</title>
                  <author>Cipriano, Giovanni.</author>
                  <author>Vandermers, Tarquatus. Seauen yeares studie in the arte of magicke.</author>
                  <author>Hollaway, Anth.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[12] p. : ill.  </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>A. Jeffes,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[Imprinted at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1595]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Imprint cropped; publisher and date of publication suggested by STC (2nd ed.).</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-B⁴ (first and last leaves blank).</note>
                  <note>Illustrated t.p.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect: cropped, with slight loss of print.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Prophecies.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-05</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Rekeyed and resubmitted</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:25249:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:25249:1"/>
            <p>A MOST STRANGE AND VVONDERFVLL PROPHE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>SIE VPON THIS TROVBLESOME world. Calculated by the famous Doctor in Aſtrologie, Maiſter <hi>Iohn Cypriano,</hi> conferred with the iudgements of <hi>Iames Marchecelſus</hi> and <hi>Sinnior Guiuardo,</hi> three excellent Aſtronomers vnder the Emperour of Chriſtendom: ſent out of <hi>Germany</hi> into <hi>Italy,</hi> to the Vniuerſitie of <hi>Padua,</hi> to the rareſt Nigromancer in the world.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Wherevnto is annexed</hi> Tarquatus Vandermers <hi>ſeauen yeres ſtudy</hi> in the Arte of Magick, vpon the twelue moneths of the yeare, where many ſecrets are reuealed vnto the vvorld.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Tranſlated out of Italian by</hi> Anth. Hollaway Gent.</p>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>a man with an astrolabe quadrant views the moon and stars while two others talk over a book. A horned devil is central to their conversation.</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <p>Imprinted at London
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="prophecy">
            <pb facs="tcp:25249:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:25249:2"/>
            <head>A MOST STRANGE AND VVONDERFVLL PROPHE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>SIE VPON THIS TROVBLESOME WORLD.</head>
            <p>OXford and Cambridge, VVittenberge and Padua, you glorious Vniuerſities of Chriſtendome, take truce for a ſeaſon vvith your deepe inſpiring ſcien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and vouchſafe to fixe your inienious iudgements vppon this rare and vvonderfull Propheſie, calculated by the famous and excellent Doctor in Aſtrologie, Maſter Iohn Cypriano Aſtronomer vnder the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour of Chriſtendome, agreeable to the iudgments of Iames Marcheſelſus, and Sinnior Guiuardo, tvvo learned Clarkes in Germany, the like vvas neuer pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lished in anie age, for the angry heauens by fearefull viſions, foredooming Commets, and ſtrange coniunc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Planets dooth prognoſticate to this ſynfull vvorld, the alteration of kingdomes, fall of Princes, ouerthrovv of comman vvealths, deſolation of coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries, the ruine of Citties, Tovvnes, and Villages, earthquakes, flouds, and mighty tempeſts, vvherby the vvhole vvorld vvil be greatly anoyde, alſo by the vari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able courſe of the ellements, all nations vnder the cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cute of the ſunne, vvil be grieuouſly vexed vvith blou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die vvarres famine, death, ſcarſitie, vvith many other
<pb facs="tcp:25249:3"/>ſtrange and fearefull accidents, as vvell in Europe as in Affrica and Aſia, al vvhich is for our vvickedneſſe and ſynnes, vvherein the vvhole earth is drovvned as in a gulfe, paſt all recouerie, except the maieſty of God be mercifull: to auoide the manifolde miſeries that is likely to fall vpon the face of the earth: and our lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned Aſtrologiſions hath published this fearefull and vvonderfull Propheſie to mooue vs to a penitent life, that God may vvithhold his grieuous ſcorge from vs Myſtically ſet dovvne, for a Glaſſe or example to them that vnderſtand and are vviſe to looke into and for a diſdaine and reproofe to them that are foolish, as hereafter follovveth.</p>
            <p>In the Northen borders of the earth, is ſcituated a Forreſt trianglevviſe, inuironed vvith a vvall of Braſſe from vvhich forreſt shall flie a fortunate foule that shall ſvvim euen to the borders of Affrica, and there light vpon a golden Tree, from vvhence shee shall pull three branches of gold, and ſo triumphantly returne backe to the Forreſt againe: at vvhich there shall an Eagle that builds her neſt vpon a golden ſtee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple ſo much repine, and ſend foorth many ſecret fiers to burne and vvaſte the ſaid Forreſt, but euery one shal be quenched and quite extinguished before the blaze <pb facs="tcp:25249:3"/> be kindled. Many Princes of the earth shall ſeeke by pollicy to hunt therein, but at the gates thereof shall take a great repulſe: ſo fortunate and frutefull shall this Forreſt be, and ſo inuincible her tovvers of braſſe, that all the kingdomes of the earth shall admire her fortitude, and grace her vvith the title of that bleſſed Pardice, vvhich God gaue Adam at the vvorlds creation. After this the Sea shall be mightier then the land, for there the corners of the vvorld shall meete and fight a tirrible battell, vvherein a mightie man shall be ouer throvvne.</p>
            <p>In the VVeaſt shall lurke a bloudie Serpent in a Denne, vvhich hath not ſeene the light theſe many yeares, but yet this bloudie Serpent shall haue many ſtings, vvhich shall ſtretche into all the corners of Europe, &amp; be annoyance to the vvhole ſtate of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtendome: Then from the Northe shall corne a Dragon, that shall breake out the Serpents teeth, and pluck foorth his ſtings that he shall neither bite nor ſting, yet shall the Serpent keepe his Den, and receiue ſuccour from the Eagle in the golden ſteeple.</p>
            <p>In the South shall liue a VVolfe vpon the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons bloud, and quaffe dovvne tovvn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> into his thir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtie throate but in the middeſt of this bloudie danquet shall he choake himſelfe and die.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:25249:4"/>
            <p>Out of the Eaſt shall come a diſmall blacke Dogge, that like a theefe by night shall enter Germanie in vvhich enterpriſe he shall looſe one of his limbes, and ſo depart vvith ſuch an yeelping ſound, at vvhich the limmets of Affrica and Aſia shall quake. This Dogge shall aftervvard forſake his maiſter, and chooſe him a nevv name, vvhereby the Scriptures shall be fulfilled. This Dog doth ſignifie the Turke, vvhich shall for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſake his Mahomet, and chooſe to him the name of Chriſtian, vvhich is a ſigne the day of doombe is at hand, vvhen all the earth is ſubiect to one God.</p>
            <p>The Flovver de Luce and France, shall liue long at varience, but at length agree.</p>
            <p>The bovvels of Spaine shall be ſpilt in ſunder, and deuided for vvant of gouernment, euen in thoſe dayes vvhen the golden ſteeple shal be conſumed vvith fire euen that ſeauen headed citie, novv more brauer then Ieruſalem shall be a place more deſolate then Ieruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem. Then shall the cleare vvord ſpring foorth and florish through the vvorld, vvhich neuer shall be ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken from vs again, after this a milke vvhite Doue shal be lifted vp to honour by tvvo golden Lions, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaue a crovvne of gould.</p>
            <p>But after all theſe things shall the end of the vvorld approch, therefore shall there be heauie and pittifull dayes vvith much vvarres and other alterations of the vvorld, all vvhich is likely to enſue this yeare follovv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.</p>
            <div n="January" type="prophecy">
               <pb facs="tcp:25249:4"/>
               <head>Tarquatus Vandermers, ſeauen yeares ſtudie in the Arte of Magicke, vpon the tvvelue moneths of the yeare: wherein many ſecrets are reueald vnto the world.
<figure>
                     <figDesc>a man with an astrolabe quadrant views the moon and stars while two others talk over a book. A horned devil is central to their conversation.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
               </head>
               <head type="sub">IANVARIE. 1569.</head>
               <p>In the moneth of Ianuarie, the angrie heauens doe foretell, vpon that land vvhere moſt ſin and vvicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe
<pb facs="tcp:25249:5"/>dooth abound, shall raigne a shovver of bloud continuing for the ſpace of an houre, vvhich dooth prognoſticate the deſtruction of that vnhappie re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="February" type="prophecy">
               <head>FEBRVARIE.</head>
               <p>In February, rumours of vvars shall fill the eares of all nations, euery kingdom vnder the frame of heauen shall muſter vvell approoued ſouldiers: traffick by ſea shall be denied betvvixt land &amp; land, and euery coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey shall be forſt to liue vpon his ovvne.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="March" type="prophecy">
               <head>MARCHE.</head>
               <p>In Marche, the maine Seas shall bee ſo troubled vvith mighty tempeſts and vvindes, that they shall ſvvell aboue their bankes, and ouerflovve an Iſland vvhere the double croſſe hath gouernment, onely be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the ſinnes of the Prince is ſo hainous before the Maieſtie of God.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="April" type="prophecy">
               <head>APRILL.</head>
               <p>In Aprill shall happen ſuch a terrible battell on the ſea, vvhereby the vvater vvill be turned to the couler of bloud, more ſanguinlike then is the redde ſeas: God
<pb facs="tcp:25249:5"/> for his mercy turn it to the beſt, and defend our inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent and ſpotleſſe bloud of England.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="May" type="prophecy">
               <head>MAYE.</head>
               <p>In Maye the earth shall bee ouer burthend vvith bloudie vvarres, and ſome nations shall furnish forth ſo many ſouldiers, vvhereby the land shall be ſo deſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late of men, that ſeauen vvomen shall bee conſtrained to follovv one man.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="June" type="prophecy">
               <head>IVNE.</head>
               <p>In Iune, a prouince in the Eaſterne climbes: shall fight in the defence of a vvrongful cauſe, at vvhich the Maieſtie of God vvill threaten vengeance, and raine dovvne fire from the throne of heauen, and ſo burne thoſe vvicked people in their tents of vvarre.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="July" type="prophecy">
               <head>IVLIE.</head>
               <p>In Iuly, the vveather vvill be ſo extreame hoate, vvhereby Souldiers shall not bee able to vveare their armour, and likevviſe multitudes shall die for vvant of vvater, the earth shall be ſo parcht vvith heate that it can yeelde no foode for Cattell.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="August" type="prophecy">
               <pb facs="tcp:25249:6"/>
               <head>AVGVST.</head>
               <p>In Auguſt, ſuch a grieuous plague and mortallitie vvill couer the face of the vvhole earth, that there shall not be ſufficient left aliue to gaither in their har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueſt f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uites, in vvhich moneth shall come out of the Eaſt ſuch ſvvarmes of Foules and Flyes, that vvill de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoure the corne from the ground, and vvhere they goe, leaue the earth barren: Oh times of ſorrovv: oh times of vvoes, oh times of more diſtreſſe then vvas that time of famine in Ieruſalem: you horders vp of Corne, repent, repent, your crueltie againſt the poore, for your extreame couetouſneſſe the vvhole earth vvill be accurſt: yet God I hope vvill heare the pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>iers of the faithfull, and defend his nevv Ieruſalem from ſuch diſtreſſe.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="September" type="prophecy">
               <head>SEPTEMBER.</head>
               <p>In September the earth vvill be ſo vnnaturall, that all manner of Cattell vvill rotte aboue the ground, vvhereof vvill breede ſuch ſtore of varmin, that the earth vvill be impoyſoned, and vvill receiue no fruite to encreaſe.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="October" type="prophecy">
               <pb facs="tcp:25249:6"/>
               <head>OCTOBER.</head>
               <p>In Octrober, ſuch a famine and darth of Corne vvil raigne, that in ſome countryes the Childe vvill ſterue vvhileſt it is ſucking at the mothers breſt, onely be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the mother can get no food to nourish her ſelfe nor it.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="November" type="prophecy">
               <head>NOVEMBER.</head>
               <p>In Nouember, a triumphant conqueſt shall be bru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted through the vvorld, of an vvorthie conquerour that takes a truce vvith all the earth, and ſets it in a quiet ſtaye.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="December" type="prophecy">
               <head>DECEMBER.</head>
               <p>In December all vvarres shall end e, religion prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched truely through the vvorld, all things vnited vp in peace, treaſons and rebellions neuer thought vpon: thus all things brought to paſſe, vvill come that hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pie time the bleſſed ſoules in heauen doe continually pray for.</p>
               <p>THerefore England caſt of thy cloake of ſinne, thy vveedes of vvickedneſſe: no doubt but God
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>or his elect and choſen ſake vvill ſpare this happy Iland,
<pb facs="tcp:25249:7"/>vvhere his Goſpell is truely preached: and let this Propheſie be fullfilled vpon thoſe misbeleeuing nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, that make a ſcorne of thy moſt bleſſed vvorde, and Lorde vve beſeech thee bridle vp the Turke, that rageth againſt the happie ſtate of Iſraell, confound the popish Antichriſt, vvith his confederate the King of Spaine, vvith al the reſidue of Englands enemies, that intends the ouerthrovv of thy nevv Ieruſalem, that vve may ſing all holy, holy, holy, to the mightie God of Iſraell: Amen.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:25249:7"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
